## **CURRICULUM VITAE**

DANIEL M. OWINO WAMUNGA P.O BOX 173 MASENO 40105

Email: dnlowino@gmail.com, dnlowino@yahoo.com Tel: +254724 653 015 / +254719 103 863 /0736 074 524

#### **PROFESSIONAL PROFILE**

A Nutrition and Food Science Specialist with over 9 years of professional experience in food security and training, food technology, Quality control, enterprise development and apprenticeship models, strategy development and implementation, resource mobilization, system administration, project management and implementation both in private and public sectors. I possess excellent communication, computer, presentation, Concept Development, Proposal Writing Skills with the ability to work with and across dynamic teams.

#### **EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND**

#### **EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND**

**2020 Sept to date** Maseno University

Msc Community Nutrition and Development: ongoing

**2012 – 2016** Kenyatta University

Bachelor of Science - Food Nutrition & Dietetics Grade -Second Class Lower Division -GPA 56.6

**2005 - 2007** Kenya Polytechnic University College

Diploma in Food Technology - Pass

**1998-2001** St. Mary's School Yala

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCSE)

Grade - C+

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

June 2015 to date Homa Bay Nutrifoods Operations Manager

#### **Key Responsibilities**

- Developed and implemented a manufacturing business operational plan for peanut butter production.
- Established the Quality control procedures for the peanut butter and ensured it was certified by the Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBS)

2010 to date Maseno Agricultural Training Center Agro processing Officer

## **Key Responsibilities**

 Coordinate and conduct trainings, demonstrations and consultancies for different farmer groups on small enterprise and value chain development (for yoghurt, jam and jellies, juices, honey processing, improved flours, pea nut butter and animal feeds formulation)

- Monitoring and evaluating small enterprise value chain implementation processes and recommending mitigation measures for quality production.
- Development of comprehensive training packages for selected farmer groups on milk and milk products in Nyahera in Kisumu West.

# Oct 2013 to December 2017 SEKE Farmers Cooperative Dairy Technology Expert

## **Key Responsibilities**

- Facilitated the training of the SEKE Farmers Cooperative on Dairy value chain from raw milk to milk products
- Conducted both fresh and cultured milk products processing (yoghurt, mala) and pasteurized milk practical demonstrations
- o Designed the products outflow within the Dairy processing plant at Nyahera.
- Quality control practices that led to certification of the Nyahera Premium Yoghurt by the Kenya Bureau of Standards.

## January to December 2017 Kisumu County Hospital Level 4 Clinical Nutritionist

#### **Key Responsibilities**

- o In charge of the Continuous Medical Education among the Nutrition Interns , planning presentations on various case studies
- Development of Nutrition Care Plans after Assessment and Diagnosis of clients at the Comprehensive Care Centre CCC.
- o Dietary Assessment of Clients and offering Nutritional Counseling on a daily basis.
- o Training of students on attachment on rotation at the health facilities where I was attached.
- Monthly Nutritional Report compilation and interpretation in Multi-Disciplinary Team meetings where intensive care is needed.
- Conducted trainings and health talks on Nutritional Management of Diabetes, High Blood
   Pressure and other Non Communicable Diseases complete with Diet Plans

## 2015 - 2017

## Lihanda School Feeding Program Local Project Coordinator

#### **Key Responsibilities**

- Developed concept note towards the establishment of school feeding program for around 450 students
- Mobilized and arranged for stakeholders meeting with international donors towards improved nutrition and communal empowerment through locally driven solutions.
- Networking with a local university –Maseno University nutrition department towards baseline survey of nutritional status of the pupils at Lihanda Primary School

# July 2020 to date German Development Cooperation -GIZ County Linkages and Coordinating Officer-Agri Jobs 4 Youth Initiative

#### **Key Responsibilities**

- o In consultation with the GIZ responsible personnel spearhead implementation of agreed activities towards attainment of project goals and objectives
- o In liaison with relevant County departments, stakeholders, Youths, ATVET Institutions and other relevant private sector partners and civil society coordinate and provide critical linkages in overall planning and implementation of project activities in the County

#### CONSULTATIONS MADE/ASSIGNMENTS

## July 2015 Seme Constituency Independent Consultant

#### **Key Responsibilities**

 Developed full proposal for the establishment of an agro industry for Seme Constituency in Kisumu County towards the employment of youth in the value addition areas for 5 years

Sept - Nov 2013 SMAC

**Nutritionist Consultant** 

#### **Key Outputs**

- o Lead Consultant in formulating composite flour of high micronutrients bioavaibality
- o Developed a comprehensive business plan with 5 year profitability ratios projections

## **KEY ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Developed the Proposal for Agribusiness Resource Center for Maseno Agricultural Training Center
- Developed a Comprehensive 2 years Business Plan for the Seme Farmers Cooperative Society-SEFACO as well offered trainings on its implementation
- Developed a Nutrition and Health Application known as MIDAN
- Wrote an Abstract that was presented at the Academia Engelberg Conference in October 2019 in Switzerland
- o Board Member: Lihanda Primary School from 2015 to 2018
- Board Member: National Governing Council at the Fellowship of Christian Unions-Focus Kenya,2019 to 2021
- Founder and Director of Nutri-Fit Wellness Services that champions for holistic Nutrition Care process

#### **VOLUNTEER WORK**

- Short Term Experience in Ministry-STEM at Laikipia Campus under the Fellowship of Christian Unions-FOCUS Kenya in 2009-2010
- The Interim National Organizing Secretary-The Kenya Union of Nutritionists and Dieticians
   KUNAD where I lead advocacy issues in welfare of nutritionists in Kenya

#### **HOBBIES AND INTERESTS**

- Travelling
- Leadership development of the Youth

#### **REFEREES**

1. Prof Wambui Kogi Makau,

Professor of Food Science and Nutrition, The University of Nairobi, Department of Food Science and Nutrition,

Tel +254 720933552

Email: wkogi\_makau@hotmail.com

2. Mr David Ondijo,

Deputy Dean, School of Applied Sciences, Technical University of Kenya,

Tel +254721316975

Email: dondijoo@yahoo.com

3. Dr. Kibet Rotich

Kenya Bureau of Standards

+254727043763

4. Dr George Ooko Abong

Lecturer, Industrial Training Coordinator, Department of Food Science, Nutrition and Technology, The University of Nairobi

Tel + 254 735508558

ooko.george@uonbi.ac.ke